Yes. So um so like just to ask about the
question about
sapana uh because people obviously want to
uh because people obviously want to
practice and find a teacher with a right
view that's probably criterium for
practice and how they can judge uh who
to follow who to listen.
You have to realize that you don't have
the criteria for what right is. So you
don't have a criteria for what teacher
knows what they talk about and which one
of them doesn't. You don't. The only
criteria a person has is this is
agreeable and this is disagreeable.
That's not necessarily always
corresponding to this is right and this
is wrong. Sometimes disagreeable things
are right. Sometimes agreeable things
are wrong. Sometimes agreeable things
are right depending on what you find
agreeable or disagreeable.
And you kind of usually it's going to be
this person is acting in a way that fits
with my image what I
you question your image.
I don't know what a sex is.
It has you're going to have some notion.
So some some some aent will be more
inspiring to you than the other and
that's fine. There has to be a starting
point. But you don't want to stop there
and now just blindly defend that aent
and not listen to any other one. you
want to see why is this more inspiring
to me. So you want to start as I always
say with something that is least likely
to be wrong which is the sutas
themselves but that doesn't mean they
read plainly clearly everybody's
basically responsible for their own
interpretation of most of the sutas
because they've been you know it's been
so long time ago and they're so general
and so condensed in meaning that yeah
same passage can mean one thing and
completely opposite thing for somebody
else. So you want to be honest with
yourself. Am I free from suffering? No. Means I
Am I free from suffering? No. Means I
don't have the right criteria. Means I
better be careful when I choose to
follow agreeable. And I better be
careful when I choose to dismiss the
disagreeable.
So having the sutas available and not a
teacher is still some hope for attaining
the right view. Well, yes, but there is
a there's a big gap
between the sutas and when people
approach it,
they usually on practical there has to
be something in between at least to
direct you towards the sutas, how to
read them rightly and regard them
rightly. Yeah. The only one.
Yeah. The only one.
Yeah. That's why we spoke in the pre one
of the previous talks. Exactly.
So even those who said you know the bis
alone and the sutas also had nav as a
starting point like
well yeah the right beginning.
Uh and if they don't find any teacher
agents who are areas
looking for
see that's it that's it. If they don't
find they won't find it. The only time
they realize they found it is when they
become artists themselves in which case
they won't need it.
So you can't be sure unless you're soda
that you your teacher is sana. But then
if you're a soda then you will know
because you wouldn't have been a soda.
So it's not a question of finding the
right teacher. That's the point.
You know until until they find the right
teacher. They'll never find the right
teacher if they're looking for the right
teacher. You need to find the right view
on account of the teacher. And then you
know that you find the right teacher
when you stop needing it.
And what can a puja teacher can do for
nothing can inspire people in virtue
but it's highly unlikely they would be
inspiring somebody in virtue without
inspiring them in the further wrong view
but it's possible if a pathian is honest
transparent and says I don't know why
you're suffering but the way I
understood the sutas is that sense
restraint is really necessary and really
important and Even if you don't get
anywhere, as the Buddha said, if you
spend the rest of the days of your life
in tears of pains of sense restraint,
you're still better and you're heading
for heavens and so on.
The problem is
once you get to the stage of being a
teacher, you are now
in contact with praise, honor, gains.
And that's going to corrupt you. If
you're if unless you're kind of there's
no right view if there's no right view
that's going to corrupt you.
Well, I mean you already corrupted
yourself even before that you were
teaching freedom from suffering while
knowing you don't know the freedom from
suffering. So even before praise and blame you were
So even before praise and blame you were
already corrupted.
That's what I mean like I said that in
previous talk even if you kind of
inadvertently oh I found this helpful
but you're presenting it as dharma but
you don't know whether that's dharma or
not.
That's a very unh wholesome thing to do
because you can't accidentally be right.
You cannot accidentally
stumble upon nibbana and then become
enlightened.
So the corruption started by by giving
in to the um you know established norms
of whatever teacher today is knowing or
not knowing or ignoring the fact that
that you do not well suffering yourself.
It's a plainest contradiction in terms
can be you don't know the escape and
here you are preaching the escape.
So teachers will probably think they
know the way of suffering they are.
I'm sure some would kind of yeah think
they know but many times many times I
heard like senior monks say I'm not a
soda but then spend an hour giving you
dhamma to telling you how to practice
dhamma. Not not just I'm not who is nobody.
Not not just I'm not who is nobody.
Oh yeah yeah yeah. Oh there's nothing to
attain there's nothing you more practice
the less you know and things and then go
on and teach practice.
You're also going to self declare also
around
that's irrelevant whether you declare or
not or whatever it's irrelevant
probably it's not our place to judge
that probably just listen what they have
to say and then
well yeah well I mean depends it is your
place to judge that for yourself
it's not your place to judge that for
everybody else in the
But you had to judge for yourself and
then you had to judge what you just
judged for yourself and not take that
for granted either.
And then see why you judged it in a
certain manner and not in the other one.
That's how you will become transparent.
I just thinking there's so few places in
the world when one can ordain and
practice. Mhm.
Mhm.
And there's no choices and then so
basically you go to another any
monastery where you can get training in
aya and then you have to just be quite
independent in some way but there also can have
in some way but there also can have
disadvantage of two independence you
become arrogant. Well, monastery doesn't
make you practice.
Non-monastery doesn't make you non
practice. You yourself do. So,
You yourself do. So,
so if you're looking for a place so you
can practice means you're looking for
practice at the wrong place.
No. Well, that's what we said before.
You want to recognize
it. You're fully responsible for
practicing or non-practicing.
So if you're not in the monastery,
you're fully responsible for restraint
or non-restrained. It does not mean
because I'm not in the monastery, I
don't need to be restrained or because
if I get into monastery, I will
automatically be restrained.
And if you start thinking like that then
it really certainly in the beginning
won't matter as much where you are in a
sense of like I really need this
environment and there is no practice
without it. It will only matter in that
indirect sense whereby are you
constantly bombarded with things you
have to say no to and restrain and and
endure or are you not and you can
actually reach find certain quite a lot
of circum like like
ways of living even without being in the
monastery they would be quite secluded
and non-distracting
and not really um demanding too much of
your effort and just enduring the world.
But you need to take responsibility for
your restraint or for your lack of it
and then you will start going in the
right direction.
I can even see the practice like of
people monks practicing certain place.
Oh, that was a good place to improve my
practice and
they change the place the practice is
gone or even even worse they change they
leave the monastery still as a monk and
they disro.
Yes. Like even the rules have not been kept
Like even the rules have not been kept
internally it was all done by the
circumstances and just following what
others do and say. The moment you step
out of that bubble you're done. There is
no other criteria reference point making
independence. Surrender to the form as I was told
Surrender to the form as I was told
once.
Surrender to the form.
Surrender to the form. The the you know
the the kind of structures of the
monastery. Surrender to all that.
Just do it. Stop thinking about it.
Just Exactly.
That's a good advice.
Don't take responsibility. Let the
monastery be
your responsibility.
Which is
not quite what the Buddha meant when he
said be an island for yourself.
Yeah. Yeah,
critical monks wanting seclusion
should surrender to gathering.
I have the reasons.
Because once you find that right place,
the right place of practice,
then it it's it reveals how ridiculous
or how uh unnecessary the external
circumstances are really.
I mean genuine right place.
Yeah. When you find the real right
place. Yeah. Absolutely. Absolutely.
Yeah. Absolutely. Absolutely.
Internal place. And I was talking about
the real home.
The real home.
It's what you were saying before the the
What's important, what's wholesome, unh
wholesome is not to do with the things
the the things out there to do.
Yeah. The things that it had something
to do with are the things you abandoned
by keeping the precepts.
Now it's on to you to develop the
principle within that.
But yes, literally like again just think
about it. If your place, if your
practice depends on a place,
do you have a say over a place? If you
have a say over duration, do you have a
say over the environment not changing?
Even if you do, will you have that say
forever? No. Which means sooner or later
that has to go, which means then your
practice will have to go with it.
I always say like no, imagine like today
you'll end up in a hospital.
By the end of the day, you have to be
hospitalized for something. How would
your mind would your mind remain
economous and different in the same
sense it is on top of a mountain?
Because it should be if you've been
practicing rightly
bombarded by elements enduring the words
and company and by discomfort it still
should not make any difference because
that's not where the difference is.
But if the thought of it already freaks
you out means well there you go loads of
work for you to do and that's exactly
what needs to be dealt with.
But even so that's mean like even when
people go in the forest and seclusion
they do it out of that projected
external reason
which is just because it pleases them
makes things easier at the time so you
don't have to deal with anything else
and and look look all the sutas talk
about seclusion. Yeah once you have the
right view sure you'll know exactly
where where the place of that seclusion
is but even that it's a relative thing
seclusion
like some people can live on top of
mountain and still live in company.
Yeah. Some people can live surrounded by
people but be completely secluded
because the company again is internal
basis for desire for distraction or
non-distraction. Yeah. That vaker is not just
Yeah. That vaker is not just
yeah physically boarding yourself in a
in a in a stone cell
padded stone cell
where you won't be able to hear see see
or nothing
nothing of the external world.
You can also say that that that place of
practice is incomparable
to any other to a physical place
because it's not a place. Exact.
Exactly. It's not a physical place.
So it overrides all
physical beautiful places in the world
that you could ever imagine ever some
you know secluded mountain stream with
the deers.
Well, there was the sutas as well when
Buddha what was that? Oh yeah. When the
man saw saw the bed by the road like a
bed of leaves and twigs, he says, "Oh,
whoever slept here last night must have
had a rough night."
Oh yeah.
And the bird said, "No, among those who
sleep well, I'm the foremost who sleeps
well." And the man didn't understand. And he
And the man didn't understand. And he
says, "Imagine you're a king with like I
don't know 15 wives that attend to your
every need and like the the high
luxurious bed and everything you can
possibly imagine in terms of the place,
comfort, sense, desire." But say
wouldn't some occasion be like that king
wouldn't his mind be gripped by
something unpleasant on account of
somebody said something or somebody
didn't do something so that fever he
could not sleep at night no amount of
wives could attend to him for the he
would be gripped by that ill will or
lust or pain says yes yes that's
possible and he said but what about
those who are incapable of experiencing
that kind of internal pain grief fever
craving can they then be disturbed by anything
can they then be disturbed by anything
no because that's actually the root of
the disturbance It's not where you sleep
or how you sleep or what elements you
endure or what elements you don't
endure. So circumstances become irrelevant or
So circumstances become irrelevant or
become
well. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. You went
beyond them. That's why like the whole
um was it the whole set of uh
um killes to be abandoned simply by
enduring them
heat cold words of others discomfort
just have to endure it. That's how you
become strong. That's how you abandon
it.
And same like when the when when the
when when a person's mind gets touched
by the pleasant feeling, the body gets
touched by the pleasant feeling as in
the possibility for pleasure arises,
they cannot resist it. They cannot help
but crave towards it.
when they're touched by the unpleasant
feeling. Again, they could just bear it. There's
Again, they could just bear it. There's
always an option, but they can't. They
can't help crave against it. And that's
why they suffer. Not because they're
touched in the first place, but because
they can't help either crave for more or
for less of it.
So that's how deeply
circumstances are irrelevant in that
sense. Even your craving is not in
circumstances. Yeah. Even that the agreeable and
Yeah. Even that the agreeable and
disagreeable is not it's it's in the
circumstance. It's not the root for lust
and aversion. It's your own ignorance of
agreeable and disagreeable.
But that can only become apparent on the
basis of sense restraint and the
precepts.
So one criteria the kujina can use for
finding the right teacher or the
teaching is why do I want to practice
dam in the first place
be very very clear what you want and
then you will become clearer as to what
you need
you don't know what you need because you
don't know what you really want
I think most of us start people start
practicing for the wrong reason maybe
just as inspiring.
Well, not being clear about your reasons
is a wrong reason in itself.
Yeah. So why do you want to practice the
So why do you want to practice the
dharma?
Oh, because I want to be free from
suffering. So then I'll seek for the
teachings that talk about freedom from
suffering, not talk about some random
anecdotal stories and and something that
will entertain me and help me fall
asleep.
You can question it even further. So I
value freedom from suffering while I'm
not being free from suffering. If I were
to think about it, how would that
freedom from suffering be developed?
Through suffering or through extreme
pleasure, which is more likely? You
already get the answer.
Things that are valuable to to be, you
know, obtained in the world, do you have
to work for them or you just get them
through pure pleasure? Which is more
often? which is more common.
So now you know okay so I should then
seek for that which for the teachings
that tell me talk about freedom from
suffering and also make me feel
unpleasant.
So you can even even with an ignorant
putinous mind you can still develop kind
of accurate criteria if you're willing
to accept the discomfort of it.